# MILAN WIEDEMANN

Wolfson College, Linton Road, OX2 6UD Oxford, UK milan.wiedemann@gmail.com ⋄ www.milanwiedemann.com

#### PERSONAL SUMMARY

I am a PhD candidate at the University of Oxford investigating processes of change in cognitive therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Testing the theoretical models underpinning cognitive therapy for PTSD has strengthened my understanding of the importance that clinical interventions are rooted in empirical science and continually evaluated and refined through research. I appreciate the importance of innovative research projects testing and evaluating technological advances in health care, particularly in clinical psychology. I value, advocate, and implement open science practices in my work. In addition to my research interests I am enjoying to contribute to open-source software tools that help to visualise and analyse data.

## **EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS**

## University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

DPhil in Experimental Psychology at the Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Thesis: Processes of Change in Cognitive Therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Supervised by Prof. Anke Ehlers and Prof. David M. Clark

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2013 - September 2015

MSc in Psychology

Study focus: Clinical Psychology

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

August 2011 - September 2013

BSc in Psychology

## University of Groningen

September 2010 - August 2011

BSc in Psychology

# DRK-Rettungsschule Goslar

July 2008 - March 2009

Rettungssanitäter (in English 'Paramedic')

#### CLINICAL & RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## University of Oxford

October 2016 - Present

Part-time Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

 $Oxford,\ UK$ 

- · Creating videos for training clinical psychologists in specialised cognitive behavioural treatments
- · Teaching and supervising Research Assistants in filming and editing techniques

#### University of Oxford

April 2015 - August 2016

Research Assistant, Oxford Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma

Oxford, UK

- · Production of patient testimonials and educational videos together with clinical psychologists
- · Animation of psycho-educational illustrations
- · Administration of text, video and audio content for online therapy programmes

#### Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - March 2015

Part-time Research Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

- · Conducting clinical interviews with adolescents for a longitudinal study
- · Setting up and managing large databases for national and international research teams

#### Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow

Intern, Social Psychiatric Department

February 2012 - March 2012 Berlin, GER

- · Conducting initial clinical interviews as well as follow-up interviews under supervision
- · Making house calls as part of a multidisciplinary team in emergency situations

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### University of Oxford

Hilary Term 2020

Tutor (8 weeks), Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences

# University of Oxford

Hilary Term 2018

Demonstrator (8 weeks), Department of Experimental Psychology

Oxford, UK

· Module: Psychological Disorders and Individual Differences

### Technische Universität Braunschweig

April 2014 - March 2015

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Clinical Psychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Practical Course of Psychological Diagnostics

· Module: Fundamentals of Psychological Diagnostics

## Technische Universität Braunschweig

September 2012 - January 2014

Teaching Assistant, Institute of Methodology and Biopsychology

Braunschweig, GER

· Module: Laboratory Experience and Analysis with Statistical Software

#### ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

May 2010 - March 2015

Part-time Paramedic

Braunschweig, GER

· Medical care during emergency and non-emergency patient transports

#### Arbeiter-Samariter-Bund Braunschweig

July 2008 - March 2009

Civilian Service

Braunschweig, GER

- · Training as a 'Paramedic' (in German: Rettungssanitäter)
- · Medical care during emergency and non-emergency patient transports

#### **SCHOLARSHIPS**

#### Mental Health Research UK

May 2018

Travel Grant

### Wolfson College, University of Oxford

June 2017

Travel Grant

## Mental Health Research UK

October 2016

4-year PhD Scholarship

#### Erasmus plus

February 2015

Graduate Student Scholarship

## SELECTED PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Berlin Oxford Teaching Alliance for Quantitative Neuroscience March 2019 Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience Berlin, 2 days Preparing for Teaching in Psychology March 2019 University of Oxford, Department of Experimental Psychology, 1 day DeGPT Autumn School October 2018 Deutschsprachige Gesellschaft für Psychotraumatologie, 4 days Psychological Networks Summer School August 2018 University of Amsterdam, 5 days Summer School of Advanced Quantitative Methods May 2018 University of Oxford, Department of Education, 5 days Testing for Mediation and Moderation Using Mplus June 2017 Figure It Out - Statistical Consultancy and Training, 1 day Multilevel Analysis for Longitudinal Data February 2016 Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 3 days

February 2016

# Universität Landau, Methodenzentrum, 2 days

Structural Equation Models for Longitudinal Data

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS & OTHER SKILLS

Statistics & Data science R, Mplus, Python, JASP, jamovi, SPSS Software development Git, Continuous integration, Shiny

Scientific writing R Markdown, Zotero, LaTeX, BibTeX, Microsoft Office

Video & Audio editingFinal Cut X, Audacity, iZotope RXLanguagesGerman (native), English (fluent)

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Peer-reviewed

- 1. **Wiedemann, M.,** Stott, R., Nickless, A., Beierl, E. T., Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Grey, N., Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Cognitive processes associated with sudden gains in cognitive therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder in routine care. *Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology*. doi:10.1037/ccp0000488 (2020).
- 2. **Wiedemann, M.,** Thew, G. R., Stott, R. & Ehlers, A. suddengains: An R package to identify sudden gains in longitudinal data. *PLOS ONE*. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0230276 (2020).
- 3. Kosir, U., **Wiedemann, M.**, Wild, J. & Bowes, L. Psychiatric disorders in adolescent cancer survivors: A systematic review of prevalence and predictors. *Cancer Reports*, e1168. doi:10.1002/cnr2.1168 (2019).
- 4. Kosir, U., **Wiedemann, M.**, Wild, J. & Bowes, L. Cognitive Mechanisms in Adolescent and Young Adult Cancer Patients and Survivors: Feasibility and Preliminary Insights from the Cognitions and Affect in Cancer Resiliency Study. *Journal of Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology*. doi:10.1089/jayao.2019.0127 (2019).
- 5. Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Grey, N., Stott, R., **Wiedemann, M.**, Canvin, L., Rankin, H., Shepherd, E., Forkert, A., Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: A development pilot series. *European Journal of Psychotraumatology* 7. doi:10.3402/ejpt.v7.31019 (2016).

## Software

- 1. lcsm: An R package for latent change score modeling (2020). https://milanwiedemann.github.io/lcsm/.
- 2. suddengains: An R package to identify sudden gains in longitudinal data (2020). https://milanwiedemann.github.io/suddengains.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

## Conference presentations

- 1. Wiedemann, M., Thew, G. R., Stott, R. & Ehlers, A. Automating the identification of sudden gains within psychological therapy datasets: A new R package. World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany (2019).
- 2. **Wiedemann, M.,** Stott, R., Nickless, A., Beierl, E. T., Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Grey, N., Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Cognitive processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD in routine clinical care. *World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany* (2019).
- 3. Wiedemann, M., Janecka, M., Wild, J., Warnock-Parkes, E., Stott, R., Grey, N., Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. A test of theory-derived mediators of clinical improvement in cognitive therapy for PTSD. World Congress of Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Berlin, Germany (2019).
- 4. Wiedemann, M., Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Predictors and processes of sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD. European Association for Behavioural and Cognitive Therapies, Ljubljana, Slovenia (2017).

### **Talks**

- 1. **Wiedemann, M.** My journey from error messages to R Packages Building tools to improve reproducibility and productivity in clinical psychology. R User Group Oxford, UK (2020).
- 2. **Wiedemann, M.,** Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Processes of change in cognitive therapy for PTSD Taking a closer look at how therapy works. *University of Pennsylvania, DeRubeis Lab* (2018).
- 3. **Wiedemann, M.,** Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Processes of change in cognitive therapy for PTSD Sudden symptom improvements during therapy. *University of Groningen, WEIRD Seminar Series* (2018).
- 4. **Wiedemann, M.,** Clark, D. M. & Ehlers, A. Sudden gains in cognitive therapy for PTSD Can large and stable improvements between sessions help us understand how therapy works? *University of Exeter, Mood Disorder Centre, The Think-Tank Seminar* (2018).
- 5. **Wiedemann, M.** Digital methods in internet-delivered cognitive therapy for PTSD: Results from a pilot study. *Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow* (2016).
- 6. **Wiedemann**, **M.** Mental health care in England Overview of the improving access to psychological therapies (IAPT) programme. *Local Health Authority Berlin Pankow* (2015).